{
  "reference_number": "11725",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "We need a solid and aspirational target now, and do all in our power to achieve it. Lock it in legislation please."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "I support Jeanette Fitzsimmons call for a two basket approach but only if methane is first cut deeply and fast supported by science.\n\n We need urgent reduction in all greenhouse gases and the Climate Commission should have the authority here to direct a rational\n approach to rapid decarbonisation."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "We must invest all we can in domestic emissions reduction. This will be a stimulus to green growth, even if other parts of our\n\n economy necessarily shrink (we can't have economic growth in a bounded system without disaster)."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I say \"Yes\" but it should only be revised in light of new climate science and only made more stringent. It should never be revised as a\n result of political pressure including economic concern."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, 5 year budgets is a very good and rational way to proceed. It allows for planning and certainty and sets a very clear pathway to\n\n help a stable transition to Zero Carbon."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "Yes, but only when the subsequent budget is set and only in response to climate science."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, the second emissions budget should be able to be changed, BUT only to be made tighter, and only in response to climate\nscience in order to reduce risk. It should not be changed on political whim. We are talking about species survival and we can't afford\n\nto be timid."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "We need to recognise that climate change cannot fit into a neat box to be sorted. It is already transforming society and our global\n\ncivilisation. So we must expect greater uncertainty. I support the considerations but I would like to add that I view climate action as the\nmost critical area to focus on, and I do not want a continuation of the myth of economic growth."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Of course. Otherwise it is just rhetoric. We need plans and we need immediate action. We don't have time to waste anymore."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Effective climate action will require a whole of society approach. Government should work with established NGO's like the Blueskin\nResilient Communities Trust, Wise Response, Generation Zero, Forest and Bird, and groups like Our Climate Declaration to build\n\ngreater and richer social licence. Government should also work with place-based groups engaged in climate action like the Blueskin\nResilient Communities Trust and member organisations of the Community Energy Network. You can gain much from the know-how\n\nand flax-roots experience of the community and NGO sectors."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I would like an independent CCC that makes decisions itself, in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS. We need a very\nstrong commitment to the long-term goal of Zero Net Carbon and a non-political body can work to the science and provide certainty\nand authority. Government can then do its job at managing the complexity within known limits."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "We need the ETS to be an effective tool. This may help achieve that, but if not, we should certainly consider a Carbon Tax."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, but I also think that you need to move away from the standard Wellington approach and bring a wider and more diverse group of\n\npeople together. The CCC will need to understand the community sector and youth as well, and cannot focus on economic growth in\na finite world. We have to get over this idea of an extractive economy and start to build a regenerative economic system. I would like\n\nto see the CCC supported by specific reference groups as well, to widen input and increase know-how as well as increase social\nreach."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, we have entered the Long Emergency, climate change is happening, we are causing it and we must adapt even as we work to\n\nreduce its impacts. I want to see government practice adaptive governance and embrace risk and experimentation as we go forward,\nto try out alternatives. I want to see government investing in community action to build community capacity for greater informed\n\naction and gain strength from the flax-roots. I want to see government providing good stewardship and behaving responsibly,\nworking to support collaboration."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "We need some short term gains as well. Please consider supporting a Board of Inquiry into a National Environmental Standard for\nsmall scale wind as recommended in the 2011 Board of Inquiry into the NPS-REG and in the 2016 review of the NPS-REG. This will\nhelp deliver the challenging task of 100% REG by 2035 - a job we needed to start yesterday!"
    }
  ]
}
